ZACK: I knew there'd be a lot of action and I knew
that we were gonna see Superman fight.
TWIGHT: It's a must for any type of action film like this
to have your physical training...
...as well as the stunt training.
Because they're each
gonna complement each other.
We're gonna go through this process...
...because we know it's not only important
to the physical aesthetic and how they look...
...but it's important
for their character development.
DEBORAH: Like all of our films,
there's a great deal of physicality...
...and we've always believed in not just
preparing the body, but it's also a state of mind.
It has to embody everything you do.
So we worked again with Mark Twight
from Gym Jones who we worked with on 300.
I love, you know,
the sort of Gym Jonesian approach.
And I love Mark's approach to the actors
and their characters and the physicality.
It's like a triad all combined.
And the training, in a weird way...
...is a meditation on those things.
TWIGHT:
The wonderful thing about a superhero...
...is all you gotta do to look at the physique
you need to produce...
...is open a comic book
and there it is.
To live up to that iconic ideal
was not an easy task.
Mark's fantastic. He understands the diet
and the mindset.
He was tasked with bringing Henry
from human status to superhuman status.
Henry was game from the get-go.
TWIGHT: For Henry's journey on this job,
I met him for the first time...
...and basically asked questions.
I tried to get, you know,
a handle on his character...
...a little bit of his training background,
his sort of lifestyle background.
That allowed me to write a training plan...
...that he followed
for the entire duration that we expected.
CAVILL: Mark, probably one of
the most incredible people I've met.
The things he has helped me achieve--
I can only speak for myself, really.
But he's opened my eyes
to seeing past what I thought were my limits.
And the ability to crush me in the gym,
just enough that I can't walk out properly...
...and I feel horrible and feel a little sick
but I still want to come back.
It's not easy for anyone,
but that doesn't mean that it was painful.
Obviously, there were times
where he was cursing me under his breath...
...sometimes to my face,
but it's expected.
Having it be difficult, I think,
makes the end result worthwhile.
ROVEN:
Henry's work to get his body in shape...
...also just evolved into...
...getting his mind and spirit into shape.
TWIGHT: One of the strongest connections
that I saw not only with our gym...
...but with Henry and the idea of Superman
was that he's given this great power by birth...
...and with that comes this responsibility
to develop values, to live by a code.
Henry's journey was quite similar in a way.
CAVILL: One hundred percent, the training
has been a journey of discovery...
...just like Superman's journey of discovery.
Superman learned he could fly.
I learned I could do all sorts of things
in the gym which I never thought possible.
TWIGHT: He started out--
I think his deadlift was about 245 pounds.
After a period of time, he pulled 435.
And it all came from hard work
and discipline...
...and paying attention to his diet
and to his sleep and to his recovery.
And ultimately,
I think Henry Cavill is Superman.
ROVEN: Mark Twight has worked
with all of the Kryptonians.
The Kryptonians are a very physical
and physically fit race.
And we needed to make sure that
whether it was General Zod...
...or his number one sub commander, Faora...
...that they were all really
pretty amazing specimens.
A lot of the first week with Mark,
we talked more than anything else.
Their philosophy
about why they do what they do...
...and why it's important
is much more convincing...
...than anything I've heard anywhere else.
TWIGHT:
He started to get it and he was like:
"Wow, this is cool. Now I get it.
It's time to get serious."
I mean, he would just kill himself
and then rest long enough...
...to decide that it was okay,
that he really wanted to go again.
SHANNON:
You know, people, they like to talk about it...
...in terms of how it's going to be extreme
or torturous or whatever...
...but I never really found it
to be their approach.
I never felt like they asked me
to do anything I couldn't do.
TWIGHT:
With Antje, she wasn't fit...
...from our point of view,
but she had taken care of herself.
And she came from a sport background having
done gymnastics when she was younger...
...so she moved well,
she knew how to use her body.
And that gave her quite a bit of advance
in terms of teachability.
Two hours with Gym Jones
is basically work hard and confront yourself.
Everything you do in these two hours
needs absolute 100 percent of your focus.
So the gym, you know,
there are no televisions...
...there are no newspapers
or whatever distracts you.
You find yourself in front of a bar
with 215 pounds...
...and of course you're naturally scared...
...like, you know, injuring yourself
or failing or whatever.
But I also wanted to feel Faora's powers,
right, and not just imagine them.
So I knew, okay, I should go for it.
She became this person
she wanted to become.
And she noticed the effects
of working in the gym day after day...
...working very hard with stunts...
...and her character development
and dieting very, very hard.
TRAUE: Eventually, you come to a point
where your mind...
...allows you to break through
your physical boundaries...
...and takes you to places
where you think you could never go to.
And when that happens, it's a great feeling.
I have to say it's almost addictive.
TWIGHT: For me, functional training
means transferrable.
That means that the training
I do in the gym...
...improves my ability to do the actual tasks.
For Henry, you know, learning to move
his body not only in the gym...
...but also in the stunt training
was what gave him the capability to do that.
SHANNON: Even though you never
really see my actual body in the movie...
...I'm playing someone
who is very physically capable.
Obviously, it affects the way you move
and just your physical presence.
TWIGHT:
Mike Shannon takes acting very seriously.
And it shows in his character.
He's constantly thinking.
And to bring that into the actual fighting
and the conflict that he has...
...in a way that's not just character-driven
or emotion-driven...
...but also has a physical component.
BLEVINS: We have hands in kind of
how they developed their character.
The discussions during warm-ups and
cool-downs was how to express a character.
In Henry's case,
that silent strength comes out very well.
In Michael Shannon's case,
it was how a general acts.
You see his posture change in mentioning
to him about how a general would act.
If they have to express power
through their attitude...
...and their shoulder and their posture,
it's usually, you know, very, very subtle.
Antje in the same way, one day...
...she came in before shooting and I believe
she had to throw somebody through a ceiling.
To see her pick something up
off the ground heavy...
...and then go shoot this scene, those things
definitely have to do with the character.
TRAUE: Working out and lifting weights
made me experience that there's beauty...
...to physical strength
and fearlessness and power.
And it actually became
a very important pillar to approach...
...to play a female superhuman character.
Because they were all doing it together...
...and because they knew
what the pain was like...
...it was this kind of camaraderie.
TWIGHT:
You put an actor in the situation where:
"Hey, if you live up to this role,
if you are believable in this role...
...you're gonna be the guy,
you're gonna be the next guy."
CAVILL:
He keeps it constantly evolving...
...as not just a physical thing,
but a psychological thing as well.
He's just someone who understands
what I'm going through physically...
...which I think is what makes him
such a good trainer.
He sees your breaking point
about to happen...
...then he'll either push you
past that breaking point...
...or he'll push you right up to the edge
of that precipice and then hold you back.
I wish I could have been a fly on the wall
watching him work...
...because he's a remarkable man, truly.
And I have so much respect for him.
It's a cool way to make a movie.
It's a cool way to get someone...
...to do something that they've never done.
And I think that that's what Mark
loves to get at and kind of mess with.
To take these people
who've chosen to be actors...
...who experience emotion in a way
where they're analyzing it as they do it...
I think for him,
those guys in the gym are really interesting...
...because pain and fear, success and joy,
all those things are present. It's there.
And with an actor,
the reward of the suffering...
...is really evident.
And you bring that to the movie. It's fun.
CAVILL: It's not the kind of training
which just makes you look pretty.
It's the kind of training which,
first and foremost, is useful.
I didn't realize, like, how difficult
the stuff that I was doing was...
...but because I trained with Gym Jones...
...I'd been given that, at the very least,
core strength.
CARO:
Any type of action, any type of stunt work...
...specifically wire work,
you need a strong core...
...and you need your muscles
to be lengthened...
...you need them to be strong,
and you need to be stable.
If you don't have muscle to hold that together,
you can get injured.
So being in shape
is an enormous advantage.
In terms of the action,
that was something Zack said:
"I want some really great action."
He has these powers
and what would it be like...
...when he's fighting another Kryptonian
who has the same kind of powers?
CARO:
Flying was one of many attributes...
...that we had to really, really take our time
to figure out. How do we do this correctly?
We went from wire rigs to gimbal rigs...
...where we had more of a base plate.
You name it, we explored it.
Thanks to D.J., there's a tremendous
amount of takeover with CG...
...but we still do
what's called a performance capture...
...where we fly our guys on wires...
...and D.J. uses that base movement and
builds over it to give it that human connection.
You're gonna see Superman fly faster
than ever before.
It's hard to come up with those speeds.
CARO: Zack and I would sit down
and come up with a scale...
...so we have some sort of rules, a playbook,
some guidelines, foundation...
...to go, "Okay, let's try
and not violate these."
Then he has, like, a riot with this.
Exactly. I mean, it's more about pressure
than it is about pain, yeah.
So basically we take that as a reference...
...and we built all the physics around the action
to see if it makes sense or not.
Most movies have three elements
you have to achieve throughout the movie.
And this one has, you know,
11, 12 giant sequences.
Thought it was just impossible to make
but it was gonna be great if we could pull it off.
CAVILL: I think the way that
the fights are different in this movie...
...is the super-speed aspect,
making it completely superhuman...
...and beyond the scope
of what is actually humanly possible.
And I think that's what makes these
particularly exciting...
...because anything can happen...
...and what the imagination allows
does happen in this.
WHIST:
There's the handoff between visual effects...
...and then picking the moments when
you put them in...
...and have real stuff happen.
For instance, the oil rig.
You see him more as a human
in that element...
...because he hasn't got the Superman outfit
on yet. He's just a guy.
But he's this guy who happens to be able
to walk through fire...
...and have nothing happen to him.
GRISPO:
Henry's very good at physical things.
Having an actor that has natural talent
to perform action is always a bonus.
MAN:
Go.
GRISPO: Our challenge is always to make
the actor do the most of his physical abilities...
...of course, without asking them
to do anything too crazy.
The most you see the actor
performing their own stunts and action...
...the more rewarding it is for us.
CROWE: It's an incredibly good collection
of stunt people on this film.
There's a level of commitment that
something like this takes.
And that goes all the way through.
Russell was great because
he had the physical ability before...
...so he knew what he was good at.
So he had a little more input
in the style and the performance.
He brought a lot to the table
with experience in action.
In the Genesis Chamber,
he's swimming through a tunnel.
DESJARDIN: It's supposed to be this
very watery, amniotic-fluid environment...
...and how else do you do that
but submerse somebody?
We talked for a while
about should we hang him from wires...
...and blow some wind
and shoot him at high speed?
But the style of the movie is handheld,
it's real...
...so we wanted the real physics
of what that would be.
CROWE: You have to submerge yourself 15 feet
and then kick off from a certain point...
...and then travel 60, 7O feet underwater...
...sometimes going through
specific motions...
...and then return up to the top.
It's a big breath required, you know?
It was super crowded down there.
You got camera guys, you got focus pullers.
ROMANO: We had underwater electricians,
underwater grips.
Because this tank was rigged...
...like I've never seen a tank rigged before.
The amount of lights...
And I think at our disposal here
we have close to 700,000 watts of light.
RIGBY: And then you've got people down
below, need to be mindful of their bubbles.
And they have to hold their breath
when cameras are rolling.
It's not very pleasant.
Pete and myself did a lot of head scratching
about how we could get the shot.
And seemingly it seems quite simple.
He just needs to be floating there,
motionless in the water...
...but we had flames
above the surface of the water.
You never wanna tie anybody underwater when
you're gonna remove the regulator from them.
Henry would naturally float feet down
and then he would sink.
So had to have lines from his feet...
...up to just below the surface, in fact.
We couldn't go above the surface because
flames were gonna go above the surface.
So we had to go as high as we could,
but tie below the surface.
And then he had just loops around his fingers
so he could still have this Jesus pose.
Then I would just have to leave him
with all the guys holding their breath...
...because they're shooting up
and bubbles can't be in it.
The danger, of course, in that is if Henry went
to the surface as the propane blast went off.
You just sink down,
you're holding your breath...
...and you're doing whatever you need to do
for the camera, which you can't see.
And I had this wonderful moment...
...ofjust taking a few deep, slow breaths
and then dropping down.
And all of a sudden, all I could hear
was my heart.
And it was peaceful and quiet
and I was down there for ages.
And I just felt like I could just keep on holding
my breath, everything slowed down.
And as a contrast, all the work we're doing
and then how rushed everything is here.
And how sort of frenetic the energy is.
It was nice to just have that peaceful moment.
And I never expected that to happen.
It's something I will not forget.
It's probably one of the lasting memories
from this job...
...that moment of peace,
which I found just underwater.
CARO: Anytime we're working with
an actor or a stunt person...
...everyone brings their own God-given talent
and attributes to a particular project.
When Zack and I are creating
the styles in the laboratory...
...before we get to actually
even sometimes hire the actors...
...we have an understanding of how
we want each person to move stylistically.
On Krypton, they're a military culture.
So we looked at that and go, "Okay, what do
we--? What sort of basis do we wanna give?"
And we mixed some Chinese methods,
Filipino methods.
A little bit of basic boxing.
But we kind of tried to create this little hybrid
that hadn't really been seen before.
Not radically different than other styles
we've created before...
...but just to give it a little flavor of its own.
WATSON: We first have to see what they're
good at and then make the decision:
"Okay, do I wanna try to push them to a level
that, say, might not be natural...
...or go with what they're good at?"
So Antje had good lines, really good fluidity...
...so we kind of made her style a female version
of the Kryptonian form of martial arts.
For the fight geeks out there,
they're gonna notice...
...that the guys from Krypton
all do similar movements.
Faora has a move, like a palm slap.
Which, on Krypton, would be
like a right hook or something.
But on Earth, I mean,
it would disintegrate a human body.
So she throws that slap with, you know, power,
and Zod'll do the same thing.
But they both have different styles.
Michael Shannon was really good
with straight movements...
...so we kind of made his moves were a little
more straight blasts and more direct stuff.
So we had to come up with a movement form
for each of them that kind of fit their storyline.
Henry could pretty much
do anything you showed him.
His character, Superman, he doesn't
know this Kryptonian martial arts form.
So you almost had to take Henry's crispness
and clean lines and training out of it...
...to give him the frat boy, haymaker,
if you will.
So that was kind of fun, just telling him
to open his moves up.
Big strikes and heavy blows
because he's a superly-- A power base.
Zod had more of a strategic style to him
so it makes for a good fight.
ZACK: We knew this was a broader
challenge conceptually...
...because Superman can't do anything
that's not a visual effect.
He can't just grab a thing and move it
without it being a visual effect.
He doesn't move it at our scale.
GRISPO:
Zack likes to draw his own boards...
...so we take that,
we design the action around it...
...and then we shoot our rehearsals
in a cinematic way.
We build the whole sequence as you're
gonna potentially see it on the screen.
We know the running times...
...and we know if the timing of the action
is gonna work out in the end or not.
We do stunt vis to figure out all the beats,
create the action...
...get everyone on the same page...
...so we have a much clearer vision
when we actually get on set to shoot it.
They show us the entire fight scene.
They say, "This is what it's supposed to look
like." Obviously in a very, very basic version.
"And this is the one piece we're doing here."
And that did make it a lot easier.
Otherwise we'd be a little bit lost, I think.
Because when you're in a green room
doing a whole bunch of punches...
...thinking, "Am I on the side of a building,
am I upside down...
...am I in space,
am I flying through a building?"
The previs helps with that.
I love it. It lets me know the world
I'm walking into.
And it lets me know how they see these action
sequences from an emotional point of view.
It lets me know the moments
they're looking to capture.
(PEOPLE CLAMORING)
A lot of Illinois was dominated
by the battle of Smallville.
Which is a big military operation
in the small town.
MAN:
Back. Get back!
WILSON:
A lot of complexities involved with that.
Lot of action, lot of stunts, live fire, helicopters,
the whole shebang.
I mean, it's a monster. I don't think
I've ever seen an action scene that's this big.
(INAUDIBLE)
And we shot it in two weeks.
So that was probably the hardest scene to
come up with, just because of the size of it.
When we did the battle of Smallville...
...we used part of what existed and then we
built our own buildings and destroyed them.
(MAN SPEAKS INDISTINCTLY)
We put pieces of airplane parts...
...and we lit these enormous fires...
...and we did it more practical
than we've ever done things before.
ZACK: When it dips and the guns start firing,
it's gonna come forward.
Yes, it is.
- Damn it.
-I know.
Couldn't we get those helicopters
that don't do that?
- Tell them you can do that?
-Damn physics.
We probably shot 95 percent of it
on the actual streets.
Couple beats we shot on green screen.
But the majority of that
was live action on location.
As much as we can do practically
is always better.
Henry's been fantastic. Total trooper.
Inherently trusts the Stunt Department.
We always show him video beforehand.
Say, "This is what's gonna happen:..
...with one of us in that situation,
so he knows what's gonna happen.
He knows that we've already done it,
that we've got his best interests at heart.
That's when we started coming up
with how fast Superman flies.
They really had to plan out every move...
...and what was gonna be shot practically
and what we were gonna be doing digitally.
David and I sat down and said, "Oh, yeah,
we'll be able to photograph these pieces...
...but there's these other pieces
that we can't photograph."
So we either had to use wires...
...or a lot of times we've done
this physical-to-CG handoff...
...where we'll start out
and it's actually really Henry...
...and then all of a sudden
when he goes into the air...
...or he makes a really fast move,
we turned him into CG...
...and then we put him back
to the real Henry again.
You Okay?
We wanna keep as much real as possible.
Peflod.
You know, we wanna see the nuances
of the face and when the hair blow by.
And, you know, the cape.
We wanna be in there.
We wanna be in it,
we wanna be over the action.
We wanna constantly push back
the digital hand-off.
And as long as we can push that
and keep that real...
...then visual effects is not taking over, visual
effects is assisting what we're trying to do.
And we're trying to keep it as real as possible
to the last possible moment.
We wanted to able to have these guys
really do some of the moves...
...so that when we get to the pauses
in the fight...
...or the moments where your eye
is gonna dwell on them, it's really them.
The other authentic thing that Zack
wanted and really paid off...
...was that all the soldiers in the scenes
are real soldiers and airmen.
They're not Central Casting extras.
I think every one of them had deployed at least
once or twice, either Iraq or Afghanistan.
They knew how to put on the equipment,
they knew how to hold the guns...
...and they knew how to be authentic
because they were the real deal.
Zack is awesome, outstanding.
He respects the military.
He gets out there and talks to each one
of the soldiers or the airmen and it's great.
(MAN SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY)
ZOD:
I'm going to make them suffer, Kal.
These humans you've adopted,
I will take them all from you...
...one by one.
One of the big fights that we did
takes place in Metropolis.
Zack said, "You know, I envision this
to be a barroom brawl on a larger scale."
As opposed to picking up a beer bottle
and whacking the guy over the head...
...maybe he picks up an I beam.
To shoot a stunt vis for that was challenging.
We basically had some wire moves.
Some walking and talking blocking.
Mixed together with more visual effects previs
for that...
...due to basically
the battle being all in the air.
WATSON:
They're busting up through buildings.
Doing moves in the air, dodging each other,
flipping each other...
...but never landing on the ground,
just continually rolling around...
...and creating this intense, aggressive fight.
The hummingbird fight got its name because
that's sort of the hummingbird thing.
You're able to, zzz, come up here
then, zzz, go over here.
WATSON:
They're able to stay in one spot, hover...
...and then they can switch positions real fast.
So we wanted to come up with this fight
that they're all going around each other.
Now, it's easy to come up with it
in our heads...
...but how are we gonna make that
practical?
CARO:
I can only do so much flying guys around...
...at the speed and the agility
in which these two characters do.
We couldn't move a human that fast
and not rip them apart or blow something.
I've never really participated
in something like that before.
Trying to build one of these, you know, epic
fights that people talk about for years to come.
I'm not the type of actor
that goes to the monitor usually.
Particularly if I'm doing a scene,
I would never go, I don't wanna see it.
But in this kind of work when you're just
trying to get each little movement correct...
...I'm actually very critical of it.
Inevitably, it never looks the way that it felt.
You can do something
and it feels very full-on...
...and then you go look at it
and it seems kind of flat.
And you realize that
there's a lot of technique at play.
And it's just about angles
and how your body moves.
Great, let's do it tighter, very nice.
And that's what Zack and Damon
especially do very, very well.
It's like these two gods, basically,
fighting over the city.
Causing destruction, but mainly
taking each other out, you know...
...that's what you wanna get.
That's your payoff at the end as a fan.
It's been great fun working with the guys.
Doing the wire work for hours on end.
There's a lot to be said for it
because you get to fly. Ha, ha.
And that is fun.
When you're doing something
which is physically taxing...
...and all around tricky to do...
...because it's so new...
...it makes it that much easier when you've got
guys who are actually enjoying it with you.
And having a laugh and having fun and
working exceptionally hard to get it right too.
SUPERMAN:
You might want to step back a little bit.
Maybe a little bit more.
We're still waiting for the easy part of the movie
to show up and it hasn't shown up yet, so...
(YELLS)